Guide to the Dept. of Economics records, 1938-2005 UA.25.17.0002
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Dept. of Economics records
1938-2005
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Duke University. Department of Economics
UA.25.17.0002
11 Linear Feet
The study of economics has a long history at Duke University. Economics classes were taught at Trinity College, the forerunner of Duke University, as early as the 1899-1900 academic year. Several individuals particularly important to the Department's development and programming: include Calvin Bryce Hoover; Joseph J. Spengler; H. Gregg Lewis; and Martin Bronfenbrenner. The collection contains miscellaneous office files associated with the daily operations of the Department of Economics including: correspondence, memoranda, class schedules, faculty rosters and files, reports, and undergraduate honors theses. Also present are the Working Papers in Economics produced by the Department of Economics, Duke University dating 1981-1990, 1992.
11,000 Items
Access Restrictions
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
For a period of twenty-five years from the origin of the material, permission in writing from the office of origin and the University Archivist is required for use. After twenty-five years, records that have been processed may be consulted with the permission of the University Archivist.
In off-site storage; 48 hours advance notice is required for use.
Provenance
The Dept. of Economics records were received by the University Archives as a transfer in 1975-2003 and 2008.
Historical Note
Economics classes were taught at Trinity College, the forerunner of Duke University, as early as the 1899-1900 academic year, but it was not a distinct discipline until 1902 when William Henry Glasson, Ph.D. from Columbia University, came to Durham as Professor of Political Economy and Social Science. In 1908 he became Head of the Department of Economics and Social Science.
The Department of Economics and Social Science was represented in Duke University's first bulletin (1924-1925) as consisting of two branches, Political Science and a combination of Economics and Business Administration. Faculty numbers within the department grew slowly at first, from one in 1899 to two in 1902 and three in 1923. In the late 1920s and the early 1930s the economics branch of the department began to operate more effectively due to the arrival and contributions of the following individuals, Calvin B. Hoover in 1925, Charles E. Landon in 1926, and Earl J. Hamilton in 1927, and in 1925 Robert Wilson who developed what was later (1934) to become the Department of Political Science. Economics and Business Administration were divided into two separate departments in 1967.
Beginning in the 1930s and continuing for several decades afterwards great emphasis was placed upon research despite high teaching load required by faculty members. Importance was also given to identifying weaknesses in the library holdings and promoting the acquisition of new items.
Collection Overview
Collection contains miscellaneous office files associated with the daily operations of the Department of Economics including: correspondence, memoranda, sound recordings, class schedules, faculty rosters and files, reports, undergraduate honors theses, and material concerning TIPS (Teaching Information Processing System) a programmed learning technique developed at Duke. Also present are the Working Papers in Economics produced by the Department of Economics, Duke University dating 1981-1990, 1992. Accession UA2008-0047 largely includes files pertaining to the Triangle Census Research Data Center. This accession is restricted for 25 years from date of origin of the material.
Collection Arrangement
The collection is divided into four series: Subject files; Journals and Honors papers; Working Papers; TIPS (Teaching Information Processing System) and accession UA2008-0047. The materials in the collection range in date from 1938-2005.
Related Material
John O. Blackburn, Chancellor, Records, 1971-1976.
University Archives, Duke University.
Calvin B. Hoover papers, 1929-1988 (bulk 1929-1968).
University Archives, Duke University.
Abstracts and complete Working Papers in Economics from 1995-2007 can be accessed through Duke University's Dept. of Economics website at: http://www.econ.duke.edu/working_papers/working_papers.php
Economics -- Study and teaching (Higher) -- United States; Economics; Sound recordings; Duke University. Department of Economics; Duke University. Department of Economics; Duke University -- History
- Subject files, 1938-1997, 3 boxes
  - Class Schedules, 1938-1976 (Box 1)
  - Blackburn, John O., 1964-1978 (Box 1)
  - Bronfenbrenner, Martin, 1974-1985 (Box 1)
  - Bronfenbrenner, Martin, Memorial Lecture, December 5, 1997 (includes color photographs and an audio cassette of the lecture) (Box 1)
  - Course Curriculum, 1961-1970 (Box 1)
  - Davies, D.G. (Chairman) Correspondence, 1971 (Box 1)
  - Dept. of Economics and Business Administration Evaluation for the Southern Association of Colleges and Schools, 1965 (Box 1)
  - Economics 155, 1974 (Box 1)
  - Economics and Business Administration Department, 1947-1967 (Box 1)
  - Economics Class Schedules, 1969-1973 (Box 1)
  - Economics Course Outlines, 1971 (Box 1)
  - Executive Committee of the Graduate Faculty, 1963-1964 (Box 1)
  - Faculty Publications, 1960-1961 (Box 1)
  - [Faculty] Publication Lists, 1969 (Box 1)
  - Faculty Rosters 1944-1973 (2 folders) (Box 2)
  - Geography course, 1966-1967 (Box 2)
  - Letters, 1971-1973 (Box 2)
  - MBA Ad Hoc Committee, February 8, 1968 (Box 2)
  - Memoranda, 1970-1973(2 folders) (Box 2)
  - NDEA Fellowship, 1965 (Box 2)
  - Newsletter, Oeconophile, 1975-1977 (Box 2)
  - Programmed Documentation of the PSSH, 1965-1967 (Box 2)
  - PSSH Working Papers for Data Handling (Box 2)
  - Population Studies Program, 1965 (Box 2)
  - Reports (Box 3)
    - 1979 (Kelley) The Economics Department: Past, Present, and Future a challenge for the 1980's (2 copies) (Box 3)
    - 1981 (Weintraub) Duke's Graduate Program in Economics: 1972-1981 (Box 3)
  - Saville, Lloyd, 1964-1972 (Box 3)
  - Tuthill, R.L., 1973-1984 (Box 3)
- Journals and Honors Papers, 1991-1996, 1 boxes
  - Duke Journal of Economics, v. 4 (Spring 1992), v. 5 (Spring 1993), v. 8 (Spring 1996) (2 copies) (Box 4)
  - Honors Papers
    - Alessandria, George A. "Japanese Capital Markets in an era of Global Capital Liberalization," 1992 (Box 4)
    - Barholdson, John A. "The impact of the luxury tax on the boat-building industry," 1992 (Box 4)
    - Carrier, Thomas F., "Comparative U.S.-Japanese Management Philosophies and Industrial Structures," 1991 (Box 4)
    - Cooper, Andrew, " A cross-industry analysis of hospital utilization among members of a North Carolina HMO," 1992 (Box 4)
    - Fishman, David L., "The debate on capital markets regulation: How six areas of society analyze the policy issue, " 1992 (Box 4)
    - Funari, Carla, "cable regulation: How does governmental regulation influence the cable-provider industry?" 1996 (Box 4)
    - Hanke, Skip, "The aggregate economic effects of downsizing the United States Navy: a policy process study," 1992 (Box 4)
    - Harrison, Katherine L. "Explaining the anomalies: an experimental test of the determinants of giving in public goods experiments," 1996 (Box 4)
- Working Papers, 1981-1992, 2 boxes
  - Working Papers in Economics, 1981-1986 (Box 5)
    - 81-01-81-12 (Box 5)
    - 82-1 thru 82-13; 82-17 thru 82-23 (Box 5)
    - 83-01 thru 83-05; 83-11 (Box 5)
    - 84-01 thru 84-14 (Box 5)
    - 85-01 thru 85-12 (Box 5)
    - 86-01 thru 86-19 (Box 5)
  - Working Papers in Economics, 1987-1992 (Box 6)
    - 87-00 thru 87-08 (Box 6)
    - 88-01 thru 88-04; 88-06 thru 88-08 (Box 6)
    - 89-01 thru 89-05 (Box 6)
    - 90-01 (Box 6)
    - 92-01 thru 92-06 (Box 6)
- TIPS (Teaching Information Processing System), 1970-1972, undated, 1 boxes
  - Miami-Dade TIPS Briefing on TIPS, undated (Box 7)
  - Miami-Dade Lecture and Briefing, May 20, 1971 (Box 7)
  - Miami-Dade Chicago City TV College, undated (Box 7)
  - Miami-Dade Man and Environment Book, November 1970 (Box 7)
  - Miami-Dade Man and Environment Items written for TIPS (Box 7)
  - Miami-Dade, England's Open University (Box 7)
  - Miami-Dade Man and Environment Materials TV Course, including TIPS, 1972 (2 folders) (Box 7)
  - Miami-Dade TIPS survey form, 1971 (Box 7)
- UA2008-0047, 4 boxes
  Scope and Contents note
  This material is restricted for 25 years from the date of origin.
  - Research Data Center (RDC): Notes on Meetings, 2002-2003 (Box 8)
  - RDC: To Do, 2003 (Box 8)
  - RDC: Meetings with Research Director, 2003 (Box 8)
  - Provosts' Draft Letters, 2002 (Box 8)
  - Triangle Census Research Data Center (TCRDC): Annual Report, 2003 (Box 8)
  - TCRDC: Annual Report, 2002 (Box 8)
  - TCRDC: Annual Report, 1998 (Box 8)
  - NSF Supplement Budget, 2000-2003 (Box 8)
  - NSF Supplement, 2002 (Box 8)
  - TCRDC: Annual Revenue Projection, 2003 Sept. (Box 8)
  - A & S Budget Task Force, 2002 Oct. (Box 8)
  - Joint Project Agreement, 2002 Dec. (Box 8)
  - Craufurd Goodwin, 2002 (Box 8)
  - NSF, 1998 (Box 8)
  - NSF Supplement, 2002 (Box 8)
  - TCRDC: Executive Director, 2002 (Box 8)
  - Alison Hagy, 2002 (Box 8)
  - Thomas Mann, 2003 (Box 8)
  - Dan Newlon, 2002 (Box 8)
  - Office of the Provost, 2002 (Box 8)
  - James Siedow, 1998-2001 (Box 8)
  - RDC Director's Conference Call, 2003 Feb. (Box 8)
  - RDC: Grant Proposal and Supplement (includes Fastlane), 1998 (Box 8)
  - TCRDC, 2003 (2 folders) (Box 8)
  - TCRDC, 2002-2003 (2 folders) (Box 8)
  - Gale Boyd, 2003-2004 (Box 8)
  - Federal Reserve Bank of Chicago, 2003 (Box 8)
  - Duke Policy/Budget, 2002 (Box 8)
  - Supporters, 2003 (Box 8)
  - Canadian Conference, 2002 Fall (Box 8)
  - RDC: Projects, circa 2001 (Box 8)
  - Census Data, 2003 (Box 8)
  - TCRDC: Conference, 2003 (Box 8)
  - Manton & Mann, 1998-2003 (Box 8)
  - Social Science Initiatives, 1988-1999 (Box 8)
  - TCRDC: Loose Material (5 folders) (Box 8)
  - National Bureau of Economic Research, Inc., 1920, 2007 (Box 9)
  - Wolpert's Letter and Reply, circa 1997 (Box 9)
  - Robisheau's Email to Ray and Response, 1994 (Box 9)
  - Talk, 1994 (Box 9)
  - Reports, 1992 (Box 9)
  - Data-Request, Summary, Stats, Roland Committee, 1992 (Box 9)
  - Ehrenberg, 1984 (Box 9)
  - Final Report and Julie's Labor Workshop, 1995 (Box 9)
  - Roland Committee, 1992 (Box 9)
  - Report, Phil's Email, Board of Visitors, 1994 (Box 9)
  - Financial Aid, 1994-1995 (Box 9)
  - ACC Expansion, 2003 (Box 9)
  - Knight Commission/Athletics, 2002 (Box 9)
  - Executive Committee of the Academic Council, 2001-2003 (Box 9)
  - Tenure and Promotion, Women's Network, and Ken Pye, 1977 (Box 9)
  - Letters of Appointment to Committees, 1976-1979 (Box 9)
  - Wardropper Committee-Self Study Proposal, 1978-1979 (Box 9)
  - Committees, Ph.D. Exams, etc., 1972 (Box 9)
  - Final Report of Committee to Review Graduate Program, 1977 (Box 9)
  - University Committees, 1975 (Box 9)
  - Committees: Affirmative Action, Judicial Board, etc., 1972 (Box 9)
  - University Research Council Grant Application, 1984 (Box 9)
  - University Research Council Grant, 1984-1985 (Box 9)
  - NSF Grants, 1988 (2 folders) (Box 9)
  - Southern Economic Association, 1999 (3 folders) (Box 9)
  - TRDC, 1998 (Box 9)
  - Completed Projects: Cook, 2000-2002 (Box 9)
  - Completed Projects: Ravenscroft, 2001 (Box 9)
  - Completed Projects: Tinsley, 2000-2001 (Box 9)
  - NSF, 1998-2004 (2 folders) (Box 9)
  - Joint Project Agreement, 2001-2002 (Box 9)
  - Inquiries, 2002-2005 (Box 9)
  - Projects: Chen, circa 2002 (Box 9)
  - Projects: Conway, 2003 (Box 9)
  - Projects: Emm, 2003 (Box 9)
  - Projects: Saunders, 2001 (Box 9)
  - Projects: Vigdor, 2003 (Box 9)
  - Projects: Bennear, 2004 (Box 9)
  - RDU Annual Meeting, 2002 (Box 9)
  - RDC Directors Conference Calls, 2002 (Box 10)
  - Census/Stat Can Conference, 2002 (Box 10)
  - TCRDC Review Board Meeting, 2001 March 22 (Box 10)
  - Review Board Meeting, 2001 Sept. 12 (Box 10)
  - TCRDC Review Board Meeting, 2002 May 30 (Box 10)
  - RDC Research Conference, 2003 Jan. 6 (Box 10)
  - RDC Administration, 2003 (Box 10)
  - RDC Directors Notes, 2002 (Box 10)
  - Possible TCRDC Seminars, 2000-2001 (Box 10)
  - TCRDC Summer Series, 2000-2001 (Box 10)
  - TCRDC Informational Workshop, 2000 (Box 10)
  - Proposed Projects: Yi, 2002 (Box 10)
  - Projects Pending Approval, 2002 (2 folders) (Box 10)
  - Potential Researches, 2003-2004 (Box 10)
  - Withdrawn Projects, 2001-2002 (Box 11)
  - NSF-ITR, 2004 (Box 11)
  - RDC Annual Report (2003), 1998-2003 (2 folders) (Box 11)
  - Stallard and Schwartz, 2002-2003 (Box 11)